a 10 kilogram block is attached to a 20
kilogram pulley
which is a solid disk of radius 2 meters
the block is released from rest
causing the disc to spin
what is the angular acceleration of the
disk
and how fast is the block falling after
eight seconds
so how can we calculate the angular
acceleration of the disk
what do we need to
do well let's identify the forces that
are in play here
so let's say that capital m represents
the mass of the disk
and lowercase m
not sure how that happened but lowercase
m represents the mass of the block
now the block experience a downward
weight force of mg
and there's an upward tension force
that slows down the descent of the block
and that tension force also causes
the disc
to spin in the clockwise direction
so with this information
how can we use it to calculate the angle
acceleration
now i'm going to describe t as being
ft
so that's the tension force
so i don't confuse that with torque
so what we can do at this point is write
an expression for the net torque acting
on the disk
now there's only one force acting on a
disk
which is the tension force and torque is
force
times the moment arm which in this case
is the radius of the circle
so the net torque acting on the solid
disc
is the tension force
multiplied by the radius of the circle
now let's focus on the net force on a
block
by the way the disc is held in place
so the disc is allowed to spin but it
can't accelerate upward or downward only
the block can accelerate downward
so we have to deal with the net force of
the block
so the net force in the y direction
of the block
it's based on these two forces
so we have an upward tension force
so it's going to be positive because
it's directed in the positive y
direction
plus the downward weight force
which is negative
since it's going in a negative y
direction
now the net force
based on newton's second law is mass
times acceleration
so let's solve for the tension force
let's move this term to that side
so m a
plus mg where a is in the y direction
that's going to be equal to the tension
force
now here's the question for you
m a should it be positive or negative
because the block is accelerating and
the negative y direction is going down
we need to put a negative in front of it
so we can say that the tension force
is equal to positive mg
minus
ma
so now at this point what i'm going to
do is replace the tension force in this
equation
with mg
minus ma
so the net torque
acting on a disc
is going to be mg
minus ma
times the radius
so now since i'm running out of space
let's
erase a few things
now the acceleration or rather the
linear acceleration is equal to the
angular acceleration times the radius so
let's replace a
with alpha times r
so the net torque
is now mg
minus m
alpha times r
times r
so what i'm going to do now is
distribute r to these two terms
and at the same time i'm going to
replace the net torque
with inertia times alpha
based on newton's second law for
rotation of motion
so that's equal to mgr
minus
m alpha times r squared
now my goal is to calculate the angle
acceleration so i need to isolate this
term
so what i'm going to do now is take this
term move it to the left side
so inertia times alpha plus
m alpha r squared
is equal to mgr
now this is the net torque acting on the
disc
so this is the inertia
of the disc
so right now let's factor out alpha
so what we're going to have
is alpha
multiplied by the inertia of the disk
plus
mr squared
and that's equal to mgr
so for this particular problem
the angular acceleration can be
calculated by taking the mass of the
block
multiplying by the gravitational
acceleration times the radius of the
disk
divided by the inertia of the disk
plus mr squared where lowercase m is the
mass of the block
so now let's go ahead and calculate
alpha
so that's going to be a mass of 10
times the gravitational acceleration of
9.8 the radius of the disk is 2 meters
now i represents the inertia
and the inertia of a solid disk is one
half
m r squared
so the mass of the disk is 20
and the radius is 2.
so half of 20 is 10
and 10 times 2 squared is 40.
so the inertia of the disk is 40
plus mr squared which is going to be 10
times r squared which is 2 squared
so 10 times 9.8 is 98 multiplied by 2 so
that's
196.
10 times 2 squared is 40 plus another 40
that's going to be 80.
so alpha is 196
divided by 80.
and so that's going to be 2.45
radians
per second squared
and so that's how you can calculate the
angular acceleration
of the disk
so that's how fast it's accelerating in
this direction
now what about part b
how fast is the block falling after
eight seconds
so how can we find that answer
well the first thing we need to do
is calculate the linear acceleration of
the disk
if we could find that
then we could find out the acceleration
of the block as it falls down because
they have to be the same because they're
attached to a rope
and so they're going to move at the same
rate
the linear acceleration of the disk is
alpha times r
so we have alpha which is 2.45
and the radius of the circle or the disk
is 2 meters
so 2.45 times 2
is 4.9
so the linear acceleration of the system
is 4.9 meters per second squared
and so that's the acceleration of the
block as it descends down
so now we could find the final speed of
the block
as it falls for 8 seconds
so the final speed
is going to be the initial speed plus
at
the initial speed is zero because the
block was released from rest
and the linear acceleration is 4.9
multiplied by 8.
so 4.9 times 8
is 39.2 meters per second
so that's the speed of the block after
eight seconds
now if we wanted to find the velocity of
the block
this would have to be negative
the acceleration technically is negative
for the block because
it's accelerating in a negative y
direction and so the velocity is
negative 39.2 meters per second
after eight seconds
now let's say if you wanted to find the
distance
at which the block
fell
for these eight seconds what would you
do
so once you have alpha
and once you have the final speed you
can easily find the distance at which
the object fell
so you can use this equation v final
squared is equal to v initial squared
plus
2ad
so you know the final speed is 39.2
once you square it the negative sign
doesn't matter the initial speed is 0
and you have the linear acceleration
which is 4.9
so now you can find d the vertical
displacement of the object
so it's 39.2 squared
which is 1536.64
and 2 times 4.9 is 9.8
so take
1536.64 and divided by
9.8
and so d
is
156.8 meters
so that's how far the object fell
mean in the block
that's how far it fell after eight
seconds
so consider this problem
we have a five kilogram mass
attached to a 20 kilogram pulley
which is a solid disc and let's say the
radius of the pulley
is 3 meters
and that's attached to a hanging mass of
10 kilograms
now once the system is released from
rest
we know the system is going to
accelerate in this direction
how can we calculate the acceleration
of the entire system
so if you want to try this problem feel
free to do so
and
see if you can get the right answer
pause the video if you want to try it
so i'm going to show you two ways in
which you get the answer
a quick and simple way
and also
a step-by-step procedure if you want to
write out all the equations
so here's the quick and simple way to
find the acceleration
based on newton's second law the
acceleration of the system
is the net force acting on a system
divided by the total mass of the system
so the only force that's really driving
the system to motion
is really the weight force of this block
so that way force
is the net force acting on the entire
system
so let's call this m2
let's call this m1
and this is going to be capital m
the mass of the disk
so the net force of the system is m2g
let's put g here
and then we need to divide it by the
total mass of the system
so that's the mass of the first block
plus the mass of the hanging block
and we can't just use this mass
we need to take into account
this equation
the inertia of a disk is one half
m r squared
now for different shapes this number
could vary so i'm going to put a
constant c
so i like to think of it as inertial
mass
you could call it something else if you
want but we need that c value to be in
this equation for this to work
so that's how you can find the
acceleration of the system
for this type of
system
so let's go ahead and calculate it
so m2 is 10
g is 9.8
m1 is 5
m2 is 10
c for a disk
is one half
and the mass of the solid disk is 20
kilograms
so 10 times 9.8
is 98 half of 20 is 10
plus another 10 that's 20 plus 5
so this is going to be 25
98 divided by 25
is 3.92 meters per second squared
so this
is the acceleration
of the entire system
so let's see if we can get that answer
using another process
so how should we do this
well we need to indicate all the forces
that is acting on the system
so we got the downward weight force m2g
and there's an upward tension force that
slows down the descent of this object
let's call that t2 the tension force
acting on block 2.
now we have t1
which pulls block 1 to the right
now these two tension forces
are acting on the pulley
so if t2 lifts up the object
you can be sure that t2 causes the disc
to be pulled
in the clockwise direction
and t1
causes the disc to be pulled
in the counterclockwise direction
opposite to that value
and so the net
torque
acting on the disc
is the difference
between these two valves
now in another video
i defined a positive torque
as a torque that causes
counterclockwise rotation
so t1 torque 1 is positive
well t1 rather the tension force that
creates that torque is going to be
positive
t2 this tension force
will create
a negative torque
because it will cause the disc to rotate
in the clockwise direction
which i assigned earlier as a negative
torque value
so the net torque of the system
is going to be the positive torque t1
minus the negative torque t2
and the net torque is equal to inertia
times alpha in the same way as net force
is mass times acceleration
so the that torque is the inertia times
the angle acceleration based on newton's
second law for rotational motion
so that's going to be the difference
between t1 or torque one minus torque
two
now i'm going to take a moment to
improve this drawn
so there is no confusion
so t1
is being directed opposite to this
tension they have to be equal and
opposite direction
and t2 acting on the disc
is in this direction
now t1 is going to create a torque
that
will cause the disc to spin
in the counterclockwise direction
so that torque is positive
and t2 will create
let's see if i can fit it here
a negative torque
which will cause the disc to spin
in the clockwise direction and this is
spinning in a counterclockwise direction
keep in mind clockwise rotation
is negative
counterclockwise rotation is associated
with positive torque
so as we said before the net torque
is going to be the positive torque t1
minus
t2
and so net torque is inertia times alpha
now the inertia of a solid disk
is one half
times the mass of the disk times r
squared
now linear acceleration is equal to the
angular acceleration times r
so angular acceleration
is linear acceleration divided by r so
i'm going to replace alpha
with a over r
and so that's equal
to this stuff on the right side
so now let's cancel r
so what we have left over is one half
m r a
which is equal to torque one
torque one is
equal to the tension force
times the moment arm which is the radius
of the circle
so that's going to be t1
times r
and torque 2 is going to be t2 times r
so we can divide both sides by r
so now we have one half
m a which is the difference
between the two tension forces
now the net torque
is it positive or is it negative what
would you say
now we know the whole system is moving
in this direction
which means that the disc
has a net torque that causes it to
rotate
in the
clockwise direction which is associated
with a negative torque
so therefore we need to put a negative
sign
so now let's save this equation we're
going to get back to it
so i can erase
some of the stuff above here
because i'm going to need the space soon
so i'm going to rewrite the equation up
here t1 minus t2
is negative one-half
ma
now we need to relate the tension forces
to these two masses
so now we need to write expressions for
the net force acting on each object
so let's start with the first object
mass one
the net force
acting on mass 1
is equal to this tension force because
there's no other forces acting on it
at least in the x direction
so the net force on that block is equal
to m a
so t1 is equal to ma
so that's the first equation that we can
write
now let's move on to block 2.
so the net force acting on block 2
which is associated with the y direction
that's going to be equal to the upward
tension force t2
minus the downward weight force m2g now
keep in mind m2g is negative because
it's going in negative y direction
that's how we have the negative sign and
t is positive because it's going in the
positive y direction
now the net force acting on block 2 is
equal to m2 times a and this is supposed
to be m1a
now because this is moving in a negative
y direction we need to put a negative
sign in front of m2a
m1a is moving in the positive x
direction so therefore it requires a
positive sign
so now i'm going to take this term move
it to the left side
so therefore m2g
plus
m2a
is equal to t2
so that's the second equation that we
need
so now our next step is to replace t1
with m1a
and then replace t2
with
m2g plus m2a
now there's one small correction that i
need to make
that should not be a plus sign
since i have a negative sign right there
so let's put that minus sign
so now let's replace t1
with
m1a
and then minus
t2
which is this stuff here
so let's put that in parentheses so
that's going to be minus m2g
minus m2a
and all of that
is equal to negative one-half
m a
so now let's distribute the negative
sign
so this is going to be m1a
minus m two g
plus
m two a and that's equal to negative one
half m a
so i'm gonna take this term move it to
the right side so it becomes positive
and then i'm going to take this term
move it to the left side
so that becomes positive
so it's going to be m1a
plus
m2a
plus one half capital ma and that's
equal to positive m2g
so now i can factor out a from each of
these three terms
so it's going to be a
times m1
plus m2
plus one-half m
and that's going to be equal to m2g
so i need to divide both sides by this
term
so this is my final equation the
acceleration
is equal to the downward weight force
which is basically the net force
of the system
divided by the total mass of the system
where you have to incorporate the c
value which is one half for disk
so now let's plug everything in so m2 is
g is 9.8
m1 is 5
m2 is 10 plus one half
times the mass of the disk which is 20.
so this is going to be 98
divided by 25 just like before
and that's going to give us the same
answer of 3.92
meters per second square
so that's the acceleration of the whole
system
so that's how you could find it so now
you have two ways in which you can come
up with this equation
you